(Watch on www.kisskh.xyz Support Admin)
(شاهد على www.kisskh.xyz دعم الإدارة)
[The Heir]
[الوريث]
[Episode 3]
[الحلقة 3]
I just went over the ink workshop's ledgers.
لقد راجعت للتو سجلات ورشة الحبر.
In the past two months,
في الشهرين الماضيين،
we've lost several more orders.
لقد خسرنا عدة طلبات أخرى.
I'm ashamed.
أشعر بالخجل.
I couldn't keep those master craftsmen.
لم أستطع الاحتفاظ بهؤلاء الحرفيين المهرة.
Jinhe,
جينهي،
this isn't your fault.
هذا ليس خطأك.
It's the rule set by our ancestors:
إنها القاعدة التي وضعها أسلافنا:
the master craftsmen's wages increase every year.
ترتفع أجور الحرفيين المهرة كل عام.
Since we can't afford it anymore,
بما أننا لم نعد قادرين على تحمل تكاليفه،
they naturally chose to leave.
لقد اختاروا الرحيل بطبيعة الحال.
Those ungrateful wretches.
هؤلاء الأوغاد الجاحدون.
Have they forgotten
هل نسوا
whose hands taught them their ink-making skills?
من الذي علمهم مهاراتهم في صناعة الحبر؟
Good riddance.
وداعاً بلا رجعة.
Saves me the trouble of dismissing them one by one.
يوفر عليّ عناء رفضهم واحداً تلو الآخر.
If those outside the family lose their loyalty,
إذا فقد أولئك الذين ليسوا من العائلة ولاءهم،
we can simply send them packing.
يمكننا ببساطة طردهم.
They can't stir up much trouble.
لا يمكنهم إثارة الكثير من المشاكل.
But if even our own family turns on itself,
لكن إذا انقلبت حتى عائلتنا على نفسها،
then we are truly finished.
عندها نكون قد انتهينا حقاً.
Jiangyue,
جيانجيو،
what do you mean by that?
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟
Mother,
الأم،
a few days ago,
قبل بضعة أيام،
when I went to the treasury to take inventory,
عندما ذهبت إلى الخزانة لإجراء الجرد،
I found we were short exactly 20 taels of silver.
اكتشفت أننا كنا نفتقر إلى 20 تيلًا من الفضة بالضبط.
I had it investigated immediately
طلبت التحقيق في الأمر على الفور
and found that you had withdrawn it, Wanyi,
ووجدت أنك قد سحبتها يا وانيي.
claiming it was for the dowry of the girl from the Eighth Branch.
زاعمين أنها كانت مهر الفتاة من الفرع الثامن.
Zhen...
زين...
No matter what,
مهما حدث،
she's still a daughter of our family.
إنها لا تزال ابنة عائلتنا.
I heard she hasn't even found the money
سمعت أنها لم تجد المال حتى الآن
for the Full Phoenix Procession,
لموكب العنقاء الكامل،
so I wanted to help her a bit.
لذلك أردت مساعدتها قليلاً.
And when I took the money,
وعندما أخذت المال،
I wrote it down clearly in black and white—
لقد كتبتها بوضوح بالأبيض والأسود—
it will be deducted from my monthly allowance.
سيتم خصمها من مخصصاتي الشهرية.
Not a single coin from the family's shared treasury was touched.
لم يمس أحد أي عملة معدنية من الخزانة المشتركة للعائلة.
It's not about the money, Wanyi!
الأمر لا يتعلق بالمال يا واني!
The Eighth Branch has already been expelled from the clan.
تم طرد الفرع الثامن بالفعل من العشيرة.
Their affairs
شؤونهم
have nothing to do with you or the rest of the family!
لا علاقة لك أو لبقية أفراد العائلة بهذا الأمر!
But...
لكن...
Don't blame Wanyi for this—
لا تلوموا واني على هذا—
I was the one who told her to withdraw the money.
أنا من طلبت منها سحب المال.
We all watched Zhen grow up, right?
لقد شاهدنا جميعًا زين يكبر، أليس كذلك؟
Even if she's no longer counted as a Li
حتى لو لم تعد تُعتبر من عائلة لي
but only as an adopted daughter of an outside family,
ولكن فقط كابنة بالتبني لعائلة خارجية،
we should at least
ينبغي علينا على الأقل
show her some kindness, shouldn't we?
ألا يجب أن نظهر لها بعض اللطف؟
Aunt Rujun, by siding with them,
العمة روجون، بانحيازها إليهم،
you'll only chill the hearts of the Sixth and Seventh Branches.
لن تفعل سوى أن تُقشعر قلوب الفرعين السادس والسابع.
Shut up!
اسكت!
She's the mistress of the family.
إنها سيدة العائلة.
Does she need your permission for everything she does?
هل تحتاج إلى إذنك في كل ما تفعله؟
Rujun,
روجون،
since we’re delivering the dowry,
بما أننا نقوم بتسليم المهر،
let me take care of it.
دعني أتولى الأمر.
I haven't seen Jinshui in a long time.
لم أرَ جينشوي منذ فترة طويلة.
Okay.
تمام.
Years have passed in the blink of an eye.
مرت السنون في غمضة عين.
Now Zhen is getting married.
والآن، ستتزوج تشن.
No matter what happened back then,
بغض النظر عما حدث في ذلك الوقت،
you're still a granddaughter of the Li family.
ما زلتِ حفيدة عائلة لي.
Your seventh grandmother
جدتك السابعة
and eldest aunt miss you dearly.
وعمتي الكبرى تفتقدك بشدة.
They've asked me to bring you some dowry.
لقد طلبوا مني أن أحضر لك بعض المهر.
It's very generous of Rujun.
هذا كرم كبير من روجون.
Zhen,
زين،
accept it.
تقبل الأمر.
How are Seventh Grandmother
كيف حال الجدة السابعة
and you, Sixth Grandfather?
وأنت يا جدّي السادس؟
We're old.
لقد كبرنا في السن.
Not much use anymore.
لم يعد له فائدة كبيرة.
It's really nice
إنه جميل حقاً
that you're still thinking of us.
أنك ما زلت تفكر بنا.
Jinshui,
جينشوي،
I've come today
لقد أتيت اليوم
not only to deliver Zhen's dowry
ليس فقط لتسليم مهر زين
but also to say something.
ولكن أيضاً لقول شيء ما.
Zhen's wedding
حفل زفاف زين
is a great joy for our whole family.
إنها مصدر سعادة كبيرة لعائلتنا بأكملها.
As an elder,
بصفتي رجلاً مسناً،
I should offer my blessings.
ينبغي عليّ أن أقدم بركاتي.
However,
لكن،
regarding the marriage between the Tian family and ours,
بخصوص الزواج بين عائلة تيان وعائلتنا،
you shouldn't get too involved.
لا ينبغي أن تتدخل كثيراً.
Jinhe,
جينهي،
what do you mean by that?
ماذا تقصد بذلك؟
A girl grows up and eventually marries into another family.
تكبر فتاة وتتزوج في النهاية من عائلة أخرى.
Once she does, she belongs to another family.
وبمجرد أن تفعل ذلك، فإنها تنتمي إلى عائلة أخرى.
You must not let your affection for your granddaughter
لا تدع عاطفتك تجاه حفيدتك تتلاشى.
lead you to hand down all your craft
يقودك إلى توريث جميع حرفك
to the Tian family.
إلى عائلة تيان.
Sixth Grandfather,
الجد السادس،
where is that coming from?
من أين يأتي هذا؟
Ever since our Eighth Branch was expelled from the clan,
منذ أن طُرد فرعنا الثامن من العشيرة،
we haven't taken a single thing from the Li family.
لم نأخذ شيئاً واحداً من عائلة لي.
We didn't in the past,
لم نفعل ذلك في الماضي،
and we certainly won't in the future.
وبالتأكيد لن نفعل ذلك في المستقبل.
I
أنا
am not doubting your grandfather.
أنا لا أشك في جدك.
I simply want to make certain things clear in advance.
أريد فقط توضيح بعض الأمور مسبقاً.
My grandfather has been upright all his life.
كان جدي مستقيماً طوال حياته.
Others may not know this,
قد لا يعلم آخرون ذلك،
but don't you know it, Sixth Grandfather?
لكن ألا تعلم ذلك يا جدي السادس؟
I don't deserve such kindness from the Li family...
لا أستحق كل هذا اللطف من عائلة لي...
and I certainly cannot accept this dowry!
وبالتأكيد لا يمكنني قبول هذا المهر!
Please go back and tell the main branches
يرجى العودة وإبلاغ الفروع الرئيسية
that even if I never get married,
حتى لو لم أتزوج أبداً،
I will never covet anything of yours.
لن أطمع أبداً في أي شيء يخصك.
As for the ink-making skills...
أما بالنسبة لمهارات صناعة الحبر...
I've long forgotten them.
لقد نسيتهم منذ زمن طويل.
Jinhe...
مَن...
I still have some work to do.
لا يزال لدي بعض العمل لأنجزه.
Excuse me.
اعذرني.
These are all your favorites.
هذه كلها مفضلاتك.
Try the peach blossom pastry.
جرب معجنات زهر الخوخ.
Benchang, it's only been a few days.
بنشانغ، لم يمر سوى بضعة أيام.
Why do you look so worn and haggard?
لماذا تبدو مرهقاً وشاحباً إلى هذا الحد؟
What's wrong?
ما هو الخطأ؟
Has something happened?
هل حدث شيء ما؟
What happened? Don't scare me!
ماذا حدث؟ لا تخيفني!
Zhen,
زين،
our family is in trouble.
عائلتنا في ورطة.
What happened?
ماذا حدث؟
Some time ago,
منذ فترة،
our family built a new smoke shed
قامت عائلتنا ببناء سقيفة دخان جديدة
and began using the Luo Ink-Making Method.
وبدأ باستخدام طريقة لوو لصنع الحبر.
Now, all the lampblack we've produced
الآن، كل السخام الذي أنتجناه
has turned out defective.
تبين أنه معيب.
How could that be?
كيف يمكن أن يكون ذلك؟
We invited many master craftsmen to examine it,
لقد دعونا العديد من الحرفيين المهرة لفحصه،
but none could determine the problem.
لكن لم يستطع أحد تحديد المشكلة.
Zhen,
زين،
the order I mentioned to you before is due soon,
الطلبية التي ذكرتها لك سابقاً ستصل قريباً.
but we won't be able to deliver the goods on time.
لكننا لن نتمكن من تسليم البضائع في الوقت المحدد.
If we breach the contract...
إذا أخلّينا بالعقد...
we'll have to pay 10 times the amount in damages.
سيتعين علينا دفع عشرة أضعاف المبلغ كتعويضات.
Even selling the entire ink workshop wouldn't be enough to cover the damages.
حتى بيع ورشة الحبر بأكملها لن يكون كافياً لتغطية الأضرار.
Don't be afraid.
لا تخف.
If nothing else,
على الأقل،
I can give you my savings first.
يمكنني أن أعطيك مدخراتي أولاً.
Zhen,
زين،
I can't use your money.
لا أستطيع استخدام أموالك.
But...
لكن...
I want to ask your grandfather for an ink recipe.
أريد أن أسأل جدك عن وصفة الحبر.
The eldest young master of the Luo family said
قال كبير أسياد عائلة لوو الشباب
that if we had that recipe,
لو كانت لدينا تلك الوصفة،
he would be willing to help us
سيكون على استعداد لمساعدتنا
resolve the problem with our smoke shed.
حل مشكلة سقيفة الدخان لدينا.
Ink recipes are each family's
وصفات الحبر خاصة بكل عائلة
most closely guarded secret—
السر الأكثر حراسة -
they would never be shared so readily.
لن يتم مشاركتها بهذه السهولة أبداً.
Your grandfather...
جدك...
is no longer a member of the Li family.
لم يعد عضواً في عائلة لي.
In principle,
مبدئيا،
if he wishes to work as a master craftsman elsewhere,
إذا رغب في العمل كحرفي ماهر في مكان آخر،
there's nothing wrong with that.
لا حرج في ذلك.
How about this?
ما رأيك بهذا؟
I'll ask my father to draw up a letter of engagement,
سأطلب من والدي أن يكتب لي خطاب خطوبة.
hiring him as head of our ink workshop...
تعيينه رئيساً لورشة الحبر لدينا...
Enough!
كافٍ!
Say no more!
لا مزيد من الكلام!
That's absolutely impossible.
هذا مستحيل تماماً.
Zhen,
زين،
I must save our family's ink workshop.
يجب عليّ إنقاذ ورشة الحبر الخاصة بعائلتنا.
As long as the workshop stands,
طالما بقيت الورشة قائمة،
we'll never have to live
لن نضطر أبداً إلى العيش
under another's thumb again.
تحت سيطرة شخص آخر مرة أخرى.
I'll keep the promise I made to you.
سأفي بالوعد الذي قطعته لك.
My grandfather once told me
قال لي جدي ذات مرة
that everything he'd learned in his life was for Li Ink.
أن كل ما تعلمه في حياته كان من أجل لي إنك.
Even though we have been expelled from the clan,
على الرغم من طردنا من العشيرة،
that will never change!
هذا لن يتغير أبداً!
On every count,
في كل الأحوال،
I cannot help you.
لا أستطيع مساعدتك.
And please, do not go trouble my grandfather.
وأرجوكم، لا تزعجوا جدي.
Zhen,
زين،
I've never intended to put him
لم أكن أنوي أبداً أن أضعه في موقف محرج.
in a difficult position when I ask for his help.
أجد نفسي في موقف صعب عندما أطلب مساعدته.
I really have no other choice.
ليس لدي خيار آخر حقاً.
We are getting married
سنتزوج
because we love each other.
لأننا نحب بعضنا البعض.
I don't want anything else
لا أريد أي شيء آخر
to be mixed into it.
ليتم مزجها به.
Benchang,
بينشانغ،
I've never coveted any of your family's property
لم أطمع قط في أي من ممتلكات عائلتكم
or the ink workshop.
أو ورشة الحبر.
I'm marrying you for who you are.
سأتزوجك لما أنت عليه.
I hope you feel the same!
أتمنى أن تشعر بنفس الشيء!
Zhen,
زين،
my love for you is true and clear as day.
حبي لك حقيقي وواضح وضوح الشمس.
All these years,
طوال هذه السنوات،
we've never schemed to gain anything from your grandfather.
لم نخطط قط للحصول على أي شيء من جدك.
This time...
هذه المرة...
This time, I was just anxious,
هذه المرة، كنت قلقاً فقط.
so I spoke nonsense.
لذا فقد تكلمت بكلام فارغ.
Don't be mad at me.
لا تغضب مني.
You have to believe me, Zhen.
عليك أن تصدقني يا زين.
Of course, I believe you.
بالطبع، أنا أصدقك.
If we truly end up having to pay damages for that order,
إذا اضطررنا فعلاً إلى دفع تعويضات عن ذلك الطلب،
I'll face it with you.
سأواجه الأمر معك.
How about I take it upon myself
ما رأيك أن أتولى الأمر بنفسي؟
and give you the money my family
وأعطيكم المال يا عائلتي
saved up for me first?
هل ادخرت لي أولاً؟
Anyway, Benchang,
على أي حال، بنشانغ،
my mother used to say that
كانت أمي تقول ذلك
as long as you stand tall,
طالما أنك تقف شامخاً،
grit your teeth, and keep moving,
اصبر، واستمر في الحركة.
there's nothing you can’t overcome!
لا يوجد شيء لا يمكنك التغلب عليه!
You're right, Zhen.
أنت محق يا زين.
It's just some lampblack.
إنه مجرد سخام.
I'll find another way.
سأجد طريقة أخرى.
I said it before—
قلتها من قبل—
we must never try to get anything out of Eighth Master Li.
يجب ألا نحاول أبداً الحصول على أي شيء من السيد الثامن لي.
Now look at what has come of it.
والآن انظر إلى ما آل إليه الأمر.
Zhen is upset with me because of this.
زين مستاء مني بسبب هذا.
Father, are you satisfied?
يا أبي، هل أنت راضٍ؟
We caused this trouble,
لقد تسببنا في هذه المشكلة،
so we solve it ourselves.
لذا سنحلها بأنفسنا.
Since the Li family won't help,
بما أن عائلة لي لن تساعد،
let's go to the Luo family.
لنذهب إلى عائلة لو.
You and I
أنت وأنا
will kneel before Eldest Young Master Luo
سأركع أمام السيد الشاب الأكبر لو
until he agrees!
إلى أن يوافق!
I won't go!
لن أذهب!
I'll go try again!
سأحاول مرة أخرى!
Even if it costs me my life,
حتى لو كلفني ذلك حياتي،
I'll produce that lampblack!
سأحضر ذلك السخام!
-Benchang! -You bastard!
-بينشانغ! -يا وغد!
In-laws,
أهل الزوج/الزوجة،
you called me here in such a hurry.
لقد استدعيتني إلى هنا على عجل شديد.
Has something urgent happened?
هل حدث شيء عاجل؟
H-Have some water first.
ح- اشرب بعض الماء أولاً.
Thank you, in-law.
شكراً لك يا حماي.
Why are you crying?
لماذا تبكين؟
Just say it!
قلها فحسب!
Crying won't solve anything!
البكاء لن يحل أي شيء!
In-law,
في القانون،
what happened exactly?
ما الذي حدث بالضبط؟
Please tell me.
أرجوك أخبرني.
In-law, this may sound embarrassing,
أهل الزوج/الزوجة، قد يبدو هذا محرجاً،
but you also know our Tian family
لكنكم تعرفون أيضاً عائلة تيان
used to be bondservants to the Luo family.
كانوا عبيداً لعائلة لو.
When Old Master Luo was still here,
عندما كان السيد العجوز لو لا يزال هنا،
he treated us with some courtesy.
لقد عاملنا ببعض اللطف.
But now
لكن الآن
he resides in the capital
وهو يقيم في العاصمة
and rarely comes back.
ونادراً ما يعود.
It just so happens that Luo Wensong is in charge of the household now.
من المصادفة أن لوو وينسونغ هو المسؤول عن شؤون المنزل الآن.
He orders us around all the time
إنه يُصدر لنا الأوامر طوال الوقت
without showing us an ounce of respect.
دون أن يُظهروا لنا ذرة من الاحترام.
Recently,
حديثاً،
he got hold of a piece of thousand-year-old pine soot.
لقد حصل على قطعة من سخام الصنوبر عمرها ألف عام.
He failed to produce ink from it,
لم ينجح في إنتاج الحبر منه،
so he's used the large order our family just took on
لذا فقد استخدم الطلبية الكبيرة التي تلقتها عائلتنا للتو
to threaten us.
لتهديدنا.
He's forcing my husband...
إنه يجبر زوجي...
forcing him...
إجباره...
He's forcing us
إنه يجبرنا
to ask for...
أن أطلب...
the ink recipe from your Li family.
وصفة الحبر من عائلة لي الخاصة بك.
Jingfu...
جينغفو...
Master Tian came to me.
جاء إليّ المعلم تيان.
He said they need the ink recipe from the Li family.
وقال إنهم بحاجة إلى وصفة الحبر من عائلة لي.
If we don't give it to them...
إذا لم نمنحهم إياه...
they might call off the engagement.
قد يلغون الخطوبة.
But how could I possibly give it to them?
لكن كيف يمكنني أن أعطيها لهم؟
For Father's sake alone,
من أجل أبي فقط،
I could never agree to it—
لا يمكنني الموافقة على ذلك أبداً.
nor can I mention a word of it to him.
ولا أستطيع أن أذكر له كلمة واحدة من ذلك.
I hesitated for a long time.
ترددت لفترة طويلة.
I was prepared to risk everything
كنت مستعداً للمخاطرة بكل شيء
and go ask Aunt Rujun for a copy of their recipe.
واذهب واسأل العمة روجون عن نسخة من وصفتهم.
She is a reasonable person.
إنها شخص عاقل.
But my mind...
لكن عقلي...
is filled with the image of you as you left this world.
إنها مليئة بصورتك وأنت تغادر هذا العالم.
Jingfu...
جينغفو...
Tell me, what should I do?
أخبرني، ماذا عليّ أن أفعل؟
Benchang,
بينشانغ،
stop trying.
توقف عن المحاولة.
Our family doesn't really have much experience with ink-making.
عائلتنا ليس لديها خبرة كبيرة في صناعة الحبر.
How much skill can we have?
ما مقدار المهارة التي يمكننا امتلاكها؟
No matter how many more days and nights you toil over this,
مهما طال بك العمل الشاق لأيام وليالٍ أخرى،
[Tian Bensheng, Second Son of the Tian Family]
[تيان بنشنغ، الابن الثاني لعائلة تيان]
you can't match what others have inherited through generations.
لا يمكنك أن تضاهي ما ورثه الآخرون عبر الأجيال.
Luo Wensong is developing new ink,
يقوم لوو وينسونغ بتطوير حبر جديد،
so you do the same.
لذا افعل الشيء نفسه.
Aren't you just...
أليس كذلك؟
Benchang,
بينشانغ،
I know what you're thinking.
أعرف ما تفكر فيه.
You just want people to know
أنت تريد فقط أن يعرف الناس
that, besides Luo Wensong,
إلى جانب لوو وينسونغ،
there's also a man named Tian Benchang in Huizhou.
يوجد أيضاً رجل يُدعى تيان بنشانغ في هويتشو.
What a shame.
يا للعار.
Now, not only is the business failing,
الآن، لم يعد العمل التجاري يفشل فحسب،
but you've managed to lose a bride who was practically already yours—
لكنك تمكنت من خسارة عروس كانت عملياً ملكك بالفعل.
all through your own recklessness. Isn't it?
كل ذلك بسبب تهورك أنت. أليس كذلك؟
What did you say?
ماذا قلت؟
You didn't know?
ألم تكن تعلم؟
Father and Mother put their foot down today.
أباؤنا وأمنا وضعا حداً للأمر اليوم.
If the Li family doesn't give us the ink recipe,
إذا لم تُقدّم لنا عائلة لي وصفة الحبر،
our family will call off the engagement.
ستلغي عائلتنا الخطوبة.
But guess what?
لكن خمن ماذا؟
Your future mother-in-law didn't budge an inch.
لم تتزحزح حماتك المستقبلية قيد أنملة.
I'm going to ask Father and Mother.
سأسأل أبي وأمي.
Benchang!
بينشانغ!
Father and Mother's meaning is clear:
معنى كلمتي "الأب" و"الأم" واضح:
if we get the ink recipe,
إذا حصلنا على وصفة الحبر،
our family will happily welcome the bride.
سترحب عائلتنا بالعروس بكل سرور.
Without it,
بدونه،
Zhen can forget about getting into the bridal sedan!
يمكن لزين أن تنسى أمر ركوب عربة الزفاف!
How could they make things hard for Zhen?
كيف يمكنهم أن يجعلوا الأمور صعبة على زين؟
Once she marries in, she'll be a Tian!
بمجرد أن تتزوج من أحد أفراد العائلة، ستصبح من عائلة تيان!
When our family faces hardship,
عندما تواجه عائلتنا صعوبات،
how can she just stay out of it?
كيف لها أن تبقى بعيدة عن الأمر؟
Feeling protective, are you?
هل تشعر بالحماية؟
My dear brother,
أخي العزيز،
if you want to shield her,
إذا كنت تريد حمايتها،
you must have the ability to do so.
يجب أن تمتلك القدرة على القيام بذلك.
Don't you think?
ألا تعتقد ذلك؟
Benchang, think it over carefully.
بنشانغ، فكر في الأمر جيداً.
One, two, three.
واحد اثنين ثلاثة.
Zhengliang.
زينغليانغ.
I swear to Heaven.
أقسم بالله.
I only just learned of
لقد علمت بذلك للتو
my parents' intentions myself.
نوايا والديّ بنفسي.
If I ever had the thought of calling off the engagement...
لو راودتني فكرة فسخ الخطوبة...
may Heaven and Earth strike me down.
أتمنى أن تضربني السماء والأرض.
I don't want to hear this!
لا أريد سماع هذا!
I'm only asking you one thing—
أنا أطلب منك شيئًا واحدًا فقط—
are you going to marry Zhen or not?
هل ستتزوجين من زين أم لا؟
I, Tian Benchang,
أنا، تيان بينشانغ،
in this life and this world...
في هذه الحياة وفي هذا العالم...
will marry no one but Zhen!
لن أتزوج أحداً سوى زين!
Then go tell your parents that!
ثم اذهب وأخبر والديك بذلك!
When all is said and done...
بعد كل شيء...
the whole thing...
الأمر برمته...
was my fault.
كان ذلك خطأي.
If I hadn't been impatient...
لو لم أكن متسرعاً...
and overestimated myself by taking on that difficult order,
وقد بالغت في تقدير قدراتي بقبول تلك المهمة الصعبة.
we'd never have been held over a barrel by the Luo family.
ما كنا لنسمح لعائلة لوو بأن تسيطر علينا أبداً.
I know Zhen is filial.
أعلم أن زين بار بوالديه.
I know Eighth Master Li is a man of integrity!
أعلم أن السيد الثامن لي رجل ذو نزاهة!
I know that in Huizhou's ink industry,
أعلم أن صناعة الحبر في هويتشو،
every family guards their ink recipes as tightly as their lives—
تحافظ كل عائلة على وصفات أحبارها بنفس حرصها على حياتها.
they would never lend them out.
لن يقوموا بإقراضها لأحد أبداً.
I...
أنا...
I know all of that.
أعرف كل ذلك.
But...
لكن...
without that ink recipe...
بدون وصفة الحبر تلك...
my family will lose absolutely everything.
ستخسر عائلتي كل شيء على الإطلاق.
Even if Zhen marries me...
حتى لو تزوجتني زين...
she'll have to suffer in poverty with me.
ستضطر إلى المعاناة من الفقر معي.
For Zhen...
بالنسبة لزين...
I'm willing to
أنا على استعداد لـ
do anything.
افعل أي شيء.
Come on.
تعال.
Eat slowly.
تناول الطعام ببطء.
Don't choke yourself.
لا تختنق.
Here, have some porridge.
تفضل، خذ بعض العصيدة.
I'll be getting married in a few days.
سأتزوج خلال أيام قليلة.
I won't be able to eat your cooking anymore, Mother.
لن أستطيع تناول طعامك بعد الآن يا أمي.
You're not marrying off to the ends of the earth.
لن تتزوج من شخص بعيد جداً.
The Tian household is just a few steps away from ours.
يقع منزل عائلة تيان على بعد خطوات قليلة من منزلنا.
Just come back often.
عد إلينا كثيراً.
That won't be the same.
لن يكون الأمر نفسه.
In the future, the person I see when I wake up every morning
في المستقبل، الشخص الذي أراه عندما أستيقظ كل صباح
won't be you anymore, Mother.
لن تكوني أنتِ بعد الآن يا أمي.
What if...
ماذا إذا...
I don't want you to get married?
لا أريدك أن تتزوجي؟
Then I won't get married.
إذن لن أتزوج.
Ronghua isn't married yet anyway,
رونغوا لم تتزوج بعد على أي حال،
and Benchang will always be there.
وسيظل بنشانغ موجوداً دائماً.
I'll just stay by your side forever.
سأبقى بجانبك إلى الأبد.
Mother!
الأم!
Come give me a hand!
تعال ساعدني!
Come on!
تعال!
Here, give it to me.
تفضل، أعطني إياه.
Give me.
أعطني.
Zhengliang.
زينغليانغ.
Didn't I tell you?
ألم أخبرك؟
Benchang's family ran into some trouble,
واجهت عائلة بنشانغ بعض المشاكل،
so the wedding was going to be kept simple.
لذلك كان من المقرر أن يكون حفل الزفاف بسيطاً.
I just ran into Benchang.
لقد صادفت بنشانغ للتو.
He said his family's matter has all been sorted out!
وقال إن مسألة عائلته قد تم حلها بالكامل!
Really?
حقًا؟
Really!
حقًا!
He said Luo Wensong
قال لوه ون سونغ
received a letter from Old Master Luo
تلقيت رسالة من السيد العجوز لو
and agreed to help!
ووافق على المساعدة!
That's wonderful!
هذا رائع!
Benchang has been so worried about this
كان بنشانغ قلقاً للغاية بشأن هذا الأمر.
for days.
لعدة أيام.
Now it's finally settled.
لقد تم حسم الأمر أخيراً.
Our Zhen
زين الخاص بنا
must have a grand wedding!
لا بد من إقامة حفل زفاف فخم!
That's right!
هذا صحيح!
Our Zhen
زين الخاص بنا
must marry in style!
يجب أن يكون الزواج فخماً!
Come on, let's go put these away.
هيا بنا، لنذهب ونضع هذه الأشياء في مكانها.
I'll take it. Give it to me.
سآخذه. أعطني إياه.
Mother, it's heavy.
يا أمي، إنه ثقيل.
How wonderful.
يا له من أمر رائع.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
I, Zhen, bid farewell to Grandfather
أنا، تشن، أودع جدي
and to Mother.
وإلى الأم.
I also
أنا أيضاً
wish you both
أتمنى لكما كل التوفيق
a lifetime of happiness,
حياة مليئة بالسعادة،
growing old together.
نكبر معاً في العمر.
Lift the sedan!
ارفع السيارة السيدان!
Here!
هنا!
When a woman accepts wedding sweets, prosperity follows!
عندما تقبل المرأة حلويات الزفاف، يتبع ذلك الرخاء!
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
Stop!
قف!
Uncle Jingdong,
العم جينغدونغ،
today is the joyous occasion of my wedding to Zhen.
اليوم هو مناسبة سعيدة بمناسبة زفافي على زين.
What is the meaning of this?
ما معنى هذا؟
Your family certainly knows how to play a clever game.
عائلتك تعرف بالتأكيد كيف تلعب لعبة ذكية.
You want to use this marriage with the Eighth Branch
تريد استخدام هذا الزواج مع الفرع الثامن
to steal our family's ink recipe.
لسرقة وصفة حبر عائلتنا.
You've truly gone to great lengths, scheming every step of the way.
لقد بذلت جهوداً جبارة حقاً، وخططت لكل خطوة على الطريق.
But, boy of the Tian family,
لكن يا فتى عائلة تيان،
listen up,
استمعوا جيداً،
no human plan can overcome Heaven's will.
لا يمكن لأي خطة بشرية أن تتغلب على إرادة السماء.
I, Li Jingdong, am putting my foot down here—
أنا، لي جينغدونغ، أضع حداً لهذا الأمر—
if you don't hand over our family's ink recipe,
إذا لم تسلمنا وصفة حبر عائلتنا،
this wedding of yours
حفل زفافك هذا
won't go through!
لن يتم ذلك!
Uncle Jingdong...
العم جينجدونج...
I don't know what you're talking about.
لا أعرف عما تتحدث.
Bring forth the Founder's Black Banner!
فلنرفع راية المؤسس السوداء!
[Hu Shunlin, President of Literary Association]
[هو شونلين، رئيس الجمعية الأدبية]
The Founder's Black Banner
الراية السوداء للمؤسس
cannot be moved unless it's an extreme emergency!
لا يمكن نقلها إلا في حالة الطوارئ القصوى!
Li Jingdong,
لي جينجدونج,
you've gone to the extreme of bringing out the Black Banner—
لقد ذهبت إلى أقصى الحدود برفع الراية السوداء—
what are you trying to do?
ماذا تحاول أن تفعل؟
Excuse me.
اعذرني.
This is no small matter.
هذا ليس بالأمر الهين.
You must not speak recklessly.
لا يجوز لك التحدث بتهور.
Excuse me.
اعذرني.
Whether I am speaking nonsense or not...
سواء كنت أقول كلاماً فارغاً أم لا...
Zhen.
زين.
Third Master Chen, you shall soon see.
السيد الثالث تشين، سترى ذلك قريباً.
What's going on?
ماذا يحدث هنا؟
Li Jingdong,
لي جينجدونج,
what do you want?
ماذا تريد؟
Zhen,
زين،
I don't know
لا أعرف
what they are talking about either.
ولا حتى ما يتحدثون عنه.
Boy of the Tian family,
فتى عائلة تيان،
you dare say you don't know?
أتجرؤ على القول إنك لا تعرف؟
Without our family's ink recipe,
بدون وصفة حبر عائلتنا،
would Luo Wensong ever help your family?
هل سيساعد لوو وينسونغ عائلتك يوماً ما؟
The Li family's ink recipe?
وصفة حبر عائلة لي؟
What ink recipe?
ما هي تركيبة الحبر؟
Zhen, don't listen to him.
زين، لا تستمع إليه.
Uncle Jingdong,
العم جينغدونغ،
what nonsense are you talking about?
ما هذا الهراء الذي تتحدث عنه؟
Li Jingdong,
لي جينجدونج,
you have no proof.
ليس لديك أي دليل.
How dare you wrongly accuse us?
كيف تجرؤ على اتهامنا زوراً؟
The proof is right inside your dowry.
الدليل موجود داخل مهركِ.
You're making baseless accusations!
أنت توجه اتهامات لا أساس لها من الصحة!
Mother!
الأم!
Mother, Grandfather!
أمي، جدي!
Why are you here?
لماذا أنت هنا؟
Li Jingdong,
لي جينجدونج,
you are talking nonsense.
كلامك هراء.
When have we ever stolen your family's ink recipe?
متى سرقنا وصفة حبر عائلتكم؟
Eighth Master Li,
السيد الثامن لي،
do you dare swear before the Founder's Black Banner
هل تجرؤ على الشتم أمام راية المؤسس السوداء؟
that inside Zhen's dowry,
ذلك الموجود داخل مهر تشن،
there is no Li family's ink recipe?
لا توجد وصفة حبر خاصة بعائلة لي؟
Do you dare?
هل تجرؤ؟
I, Li Jinshui,
أنا، لي جينشوي،
have made ink-making the calling of my life.
لقد جعلت صناعة الحبر مهنة حياتي.
Even though
بالرغم من
I haven't made ink in years,
لم أصنع الحبر منذ سنوات.
the rules of the ink trade
قواعد تجارة الحبر
remain engraved in my heart.
ستبقى محفورة في قلبي.
I have not,
أما أنا فلا،
nor could I ever...
ولا أستطيع أبداً...
leak the Li family's recipe to outsiders.
تسريب وصفة عائلة لي إلى الغرباء.
Eighth Master Li, nothing stays hidden forever.
يا سيد لي الثامن، لا شيء يبقى مخفياً إلى الأبد.
The Luos demanded our family's recipe
طالب شعب اللو بوصفة عائلتنا
in exchange for saving the Tian family's business.
في مقابل إنقاذ أعمال عائلة تيان.
I've thoroughly and carefully investigated all of this.
لقد قمت بالتحقيق في كل هذا بدقة وعناية .
And yet you still deny it?
ومع ذلك ما زلت تنكر ذلك؟
That's not true, Eighth Master Li.
هذا غير صحيح يا سيد لي الثامن.
Don't listen to him.
لا تستمع إليه.
Grandfather, he's just spouting nonsense.
يا جدي، إنه مجرد هراء.
Whether it's true or not,
سواء كان ذلك صحيحاً أم لا،
a search of the dowry will tell.
سيكشف تفتيش المهر الحقيقة.
Men!
الرجال!
Search it!
ابحث عنه!
You must not!
لا يجوز لك ذلك!
You cannot search the dowry.
لا يجوز تفتيش المهر.
Benchang!
بينشانغ!
Don't stop them. Let them search!
لا تمنعهم. دعهم يبحثون!
I'd like to see
أود أن أرى
what exactly they can find!
ما الذي يمكنهم إيجاده بالضبط!
Jingdong!
جينغدونغ!
Seventh Grandmother.
الجدة السابعة.
Jingdong,
جينغدونغ
even if there is an issue,
حتى لو كانت هناك مشكلة،
it should be resolved within our family.
ينبغي حل الأمر داخل عائلتنا.
Making a scene in public
إثارة ضجة في الأماكن العامة
only brings shame on our own family!
لا يجلب ذلك إلا العار على عائلتنا!
Aunt Rujun,
العمة روجون،
everything I do is for our family's business.
كل ما أفعله هو من أجل أعمال عائلتنا.
I have a clear conscience.
ضميري مرتاح.
If I have wronged Eighth Master Li today,
إذا كنت قد أخطأت في حق السيد الثامن لي اليوم،
I'm willing to accept any punishment.
أنا على استعداد لقبول أي عقاب.
But if the Eighth Branch
لكن إذا كان الفرع الثامن
has really leaked our family's recipe,
لقد سرب وصفة عائلتنا بالفعل،
then I ask the Eighth Branch
ثم أسأل الفرع الثامن
to give us an accounting
لتقديم حساب لنا
before the Black Banner.
قبل الراية السوداء.
It doesn't have to come to this, Jingdong.
ليس من الضروري أن يصل الأمر إلى هذا الحد يا جينغدونغ.
Seventh Aunt,
العمة السابعة،
for the sake of our family,
من أجل عائلتنا،
please indulge me this once!
أرجو أن تسمحوا لي بذلك هذه المرة!
Found it! Found it!
وجدتها! وجدتها!
How do you explain this?
كيف تفسر هذا؟
It was me!
كنت أنا!
I, Li Zhengliang, was disloyal and unfilial
أنا، لي زينغليانغ، كنت غير مخلص وغير مطيع
and stole the ink recipe for the Tian family!
وسرق وصفة الحبر لعائلة تيان!
It's
إنه
all my fault!
كل هذا خطأي!
None of this has anything to do with
لا علاقة لأي من هذا بـ
my grandfather, my mother, or Zhen!
جدي، أمي، أو زين!
Zhengliang...
زينغليانغ...
Do you know
هل تعلم
what you are saying?
ماذا تقول؟
Zhengliang, what on earth happened?
تشنغليانغ، ما الذي حدث بحق السماء؟
What happened?
ماذا حدث؟
Hurry up and tell us!
أسرع وأخبرنا!
Say something!
قل شيئا!
Benchang said...
وقال بينشانغ...
the ink recipe concerned his family's survival.
كانت وصفة الحبر تتعلق ببقاء عائلته على قيد الحياة.
If we didn't give it to them,
لو لم نمنحهم إياه،
you'd endure hardship with the Tian family for the rest of your life.
ستتحمل المشقة مع عائلة تيان لبقية حياتك.
It was my fault.
كانت غلطتي.
I couldn't think of another way.
لم أستطع التفكير في طريقة أخرى.
You... you foolish child!
أنت... يا لك من طفل أحمق!
How could you...
كيف يمكنك...
How could you do such a stupid thing?
كيف يمكنك فعل شيء غبي كهذا؟
Don't you know
ألا تعلم
you've ruined Zhen!
لقد دمرتَ زين!
It was my fault.
كانت غلطتي.
It was all my fault.
كان كل ذلك خطأي.
Zhengliang...
زينغليانغ...
Eighth Uncle,
العم الثامن،
of the four brothers in my generation,
من بين الإخوة الأربعة في جيلي،
I'm the only one left breathing
أنا الوحيد الذي ما زال يتنفس
with just one leg—crippled though I am.
بساق واحدة فقط - رغم أنني معاق.
You once said
قلت ذات مرة
that it was the Li family's support that allowed you to master your craft
أن دعم عائلة لي هو الذي سمح لك بإتقان حرفتك
and that you would repay them in kind—
وأنك سترد لهم الجميل بالمثل.
that you'd never do anything to shame our ancestors!
أنك لن تفعل أي شيء يسيء إلى أجدادنا!
But...
لكن...
what about your descendants?
وماذا عن ذريتك؟
Today...
اليوم...
before the Founder's Black Banner,
قبل راية المؤسس السوداء،
give us an account!
أنشئ لنا حسابًا!
Grandfather...
الجد...
Founder above,
المؤسس المذكور أعلاه،
I, Li Jinshui,
أنا، لي جينشوي،
have failed to discipline my family
لقد فشلوا في تأديب عائلتي
and nearly allowed the Li family’s ink recipe
وكادت أن تسمح بوصفة حبر عائلة لي
to fall into the hands of outsiders.
أن تقع في أيدي الغرباء.
I have failed the Li family
لقد خذلت عائلة لي
and their ancestors.
وأسلافهم.
I, Li Jinshui, your devoted disciple,
أنا، لي جينشوي، تلميذك المخلص
swear here and now:
أقسم هنا والآن:
from this moment forward...
من هذه اللحظة فصاعدًا...
from this moment forward, I'll step away from the ink trade.
من هذه اللحظة فصاعدًا، سأبتعد عن تجارة الحبر.
If I break this oath...
إذا أخلفت هذا القسم...
may I suffer
أتمنى أن أعاني
eternal torment
عذاب أبدي
in the deepest hell.
في أعمق جحيم.
Founder,
مؤسس،
I need to borrow...
أحتاج إلى الاستعارة...
your Original Ink Stick.
قلم الحبر الأصلي الخاص بك.
-Grandfather!
-جدي!
Father!
أب!
Grandfather!
جدي!
Father...
أب...
Grandfather...
الجد...
This is...
هذا هو...
how I answer to the Li family.
كيف أجيب عائلة لي.
Father...
أب...
Grandfather...
الجد...
Zhen,
زين،
the auspicious hour is upon us...
لقد حانت الساعة الميمونة...
Shut up!
اسكت!
Grandfather, please get up.
جدي، من فضلك انهض.
Grandfather...
الجد...
Zhen...
زين...
Does it hurt?
هل يؤلمك؟
I never thought things
لم أفكر في أشياء كهذه قط
would come to this.
سيصل الأمر إلى هذا الحد.
Zhen, I did all this
زين، لقد فعلت كل هذا
so we could have a good life.
حتى نتمكن من عيش حياة طيبة.
I truly love you, Zhen!
أحبك حقاً يا زين!
You have to believe me, Zhen!
عليك أن تصدقني يا زين!
Shut up!
اسكت!
Tian Benchang,
تيان بينتشانج,
we grew up together.
لقد نشأنا معاً.
We were childhood sweethearts
كنا حبيبين منذ الطفولة
and deeply in love.
ومغرم بشدة.
You cared for me in every way.
لقد اعتنيت بي بكل الطرق.
Between us, there was not only love
لم يكن بيننا الحب فقط
but a debt of gratitude.
لكن ثمة دين امتنان.
You used to be
كنتَ في السابق
the person I trusted most.
الشخص الذي أثق به أكثر من غيره.
But today,
لكن اليوم،
you've destroyed all of that.
لقد دمرت كل ذلك.
I told you,
أخبرتك،
my family is where I draw the line.
عائلتي هي الحد الذي أرسمه.
So, Benchang,
لذلك، بينشانغ،
this is...
هذا هو...
the end for us.
النهاية بالنسبة لنا.
Since my marriage began with this ink recipe...
منذ أن بدأ زواجي بهذه الوصفة للحبر...
let it end with the ink recipe.
فلنختم بوصفة الحبر.
Everything ends now!
كل شيء سينتهي الآن!
Fellow townsfolk here,
أهل البلدة الكرام،
please bear witness for me, Li Zhen:
أرجو أن تشهد لي يا لي تشن:
the dissolution of this marriage
فسخ هذا الزواج
is not because the Tian family refuses to wed—
ليس ذلك لأن عائلة تيان ترفض الزواج—
it is I, Li Zhen, who am calling it off!
أنا، لي تشن، من يقوم بإلغاء ذلك!
Today, I, Li Zhen,
اليوم، أنا، لي تشن،
am calling off this marriage!
أنا ألغي هذا الزواج!
Zhen!
زين!
Zhen...
زين...
Grandfather!
جدي!
Mother.
الأم.
Zhengliang.
زينغليانغ.
Let's go home!
هيا بنا إلى المنزل!
Zhen...
زين...
Zhen!
زين!
Young Master! Young Master!
يا سيدي الشاب! يا سيدي الشاب!
Young Master!
يا سيدي الشاب!
Out with it.
قلها بصراحة.
Li Zhen...
لي تشن...
Li Zhen called off the wedding!
ألغت لي تشن حفل الزفاف!
T-That ink recipe was torn up too!
وصفة الحبر تلك كانت ممزقة أيضاً!
Interesting.
مثير للاهتمام.
What do you mean?
ماذا تقصد؟
I've spent years carefully working toward this!
لقد أمضيت سنوات أعمل بجد لتحقيق هذا!
We were just one step away!
كنا على بُعد خطوة واحدة فقط!
Once Zhen married into our family
بمجرد أن تزوجت تشن من عائلتنا
and we obtained the Li family's ink recipe,
وحصلنا على وصفة حبر عائلة لي،
we would've secured our footing
كنا سنثبت أقدامنا
in the ink trade!
في تجارة الأحبار!
That scoundrel Jingdong—
ذلك الوغد جينغدونغ—
how did he come to know of this?
كيف علم بهذا الأمر؟
And Zhen,
وزين،
that little girl has some nerve!
يا لها من جرأة تلك الفتاة الصغيرة!
She dared to call off the wedding in public?
هل تجرأت على إلغاء الزفاف علنًا؟
How will our family
كيف ستعيش عائلتنا؟
show our faces in the future?
هل سنظهر وجوهنا في المستقبل؟
Fortunately, Eldest Young Master Luo
لحسن الحظ، السيد الشاب الأكبر لو
stepped in and took over the deal with Registrar Zhang himself.
تدخل وتولى الصفقة مع المسجل تشانغ بنفسه.
Otherwise,
خلاف ذلك،
we would've lost everything and gained nothing.
كنا سنخسر كل شيء ولن نربح شيئاً.
What do you know,
ما الذي تعرفه؟
short-sighted woman?
امرأة قصيرة النظر؟
Do you really think
هل تعتقد حقاً
Luo Wensong
لو ون سونغ
suddenly grew a conscience
فجأةً نما لديه ضمير
and helped us out of kindness?
وساعدنا بدافع اللطف؟
Wrong!
خطأ!
He did it
لقد فعلها
to cut off all our options!
لقطع جميع خياراتنا!
Once this gets out,
بمجرد أن ينتشر هذا الخبر،
won't it make our family look incompetent—
ألن يجعل ذلك عائلتنا تبدو غير كفؤة؟
that we can only get things done with the help of the Li and Luo families?
هل يعني ذلك أننا لا نستطيع إنجاز الأمور إلا بمساعدة عائلتي لي ولو؟
Then, in all of Huizhou,
ثم، في جميع أنحاء هويتشو،
who will still trust our family?
من سيثق بعائلتنا بعد الآن؟
In the future,
في المستقبل،
who would dare do business with us?
من يجرؤ على التعامل معنا؟
Stop right there!
توقف هنا!
Well, this is your own home,
حسناً، هذا منزلك الخاص،
and you're sneaking around like a thief!
وأنت تتسلل كاللص!
You disgraceful thing!
يا لك من شيء مخزٍ!
Mother.
الأم.
You barely ate tonight.
بالكاد أكلت الليلة.
Please have some of this broth.
تفضل بتناول بعض من هذا المرق.
Your health is important.
صحتك مهمة.
In the end, Zhen's marriage
في النهاية، زواج تشن
still fell through.
لكن الصفقة لم تتم.
Yes.
نعم.
After the huge scene today,
بعد المشهد الضخم الذي شهدناه اليوم،
I'm afraid it will be hard
أخشى أن يكون الأمر صعباً
for Zhen to marry in the future.
لكي تتزوج زين في المستقبل.
With that girl's temperament,
مع مزاج تلك الفتاة،
she may not care about that.
ربما لا تهتم بذلك.
But with Jingdong making such a scene,
لكن مع قيام جينغدونغ بإثارة مثل هذه الضجة،
I'm afraid
أخشى
they will really
سوف يفعلون ذلك حقًا
sever all ties with us.
اقطعوا جميع العلاقات معنا.
All that money spent on wedding preparations
كل تلك الأموال التي أنفقت على تجهيزات الزفاف
went to waste for nothing.
ذهب هباءً منثوراً بلا فائدة.
Without the Tian family's help,
بدون مساعدة عائلة تيان،
life will be very hard
ستكون الحياة صعبة للغاية
for the Eighth Branch
للفرع الثامن
in the future.
في المستقبل.
Let's do this:
هيا بنا نفعل هذا:
whatever Jinshui makes in the future,
مهما كان ما سيقدمه جينشوي في المستقبل،
tell them to procure
أخبرهم أن يقوموا بشراء
more of it.
المزيد منه.
It was supposed to be such a joyous wedding.
كان من المفترض أن يكون حفل زفاف بهيجاً للغاية.
And she was marrying into the Tian family—
وكانت ستتزوج من عائلة تيان.
a family with standing and means.
عائلة ذات مكانة وموارد.
So many families here in City Gate Lane
يوجد هنا العديد من العائلات في سيتي جيت لين
envy such good fortune.
أحسد على هذه الثروة العظيمة.
Exactly. Breaking off the wedding in public...
بالضبط. فسخ الزفاف علناً...
Is that girl stupid?
هل تلك الفتاة غبية؟
What will she do now?
ماذا ستفعل الآن؟
Mother, Zhengliang, stop working!
يا أمي، يا تشنغليانغ، توقفي عن العمل!
Zhen, where have you been?
زين، أين كنت؟
Let's have an extra dish today!
لنتناول طبقاً إضافياً اليوم!
Zhen.
زين.
Where did you get this?
من أين حصلت على هذا؟
Uncle Zhang at the butcher shop practically gave it to me.
لقد أعطاني العم تشانغ في محل الجزارة إياها تقريباً.
Butcher Zhang
بوتشر تشانغ
is usually so tight-fisted,
عادة ما يكون بخيلاً للغاية،
but he can't stand to see a woman cry.
لكنه لا يطيق رؤية امرأة تبكي.
So I put on a show for him.
لذا قدمت له عرضاً.
I said,
قلتُ:
"Uncle Zhang, with such misfortune befalling our family,
"عمي تشانغ، مع هذه المصيبة التي حلت بعائلتنا،
my mother and grandfather
أمي وجدي
can hardly eat."
لا أستطيع أن آكل تقريباً.
And guess what?
وتخيل ماذا؟
He sold me all this for just five coins!
لقد باعني كل هذا بخمس عملات معدنية فقط!
Uncle Zhang even gave me a lot of pork belly.
حتى أن العم تشانغ أعطاني الكثير من لحم بطن الخنزير.
He said that since Grandfather's teeth weren't good,
قال إن أسنان جده لم تكن جيدة،
he shouldn't risk chewing on bones.
لا ينبغي له أن يخاطر بمضغ العظام.
Oh, you.
أوه، أنت.
They gossip about me behind my back all the time.
إنهم يتحدثون عني بالسوء من وراء ظهري طوال الوقت.
I can't shut them up,
لا أستطيع إسكاتهم،
so I might as well get something out of it.
لذا من الأفضل أن أحصل على شيء ما من ذلك.
That way, it's not a total loss.
وبهذه الطريقة، لن تكون خسارة كاملة.
I'm not blaming you.
أنا لا ألومك.
-I’m just afraid… -Mother.
- أنا خائفة فقط... - أمي.
I know.
أنا أعرف.
I know all that.
أعرف كل ذلك.
But I was the one who called off the wedding.
لكنني كنت أنا من ألغى الزفاف.
It's not worth regretting.
لا يستحق الأمر الندم.
And it's certainly not worth letting you, Grandfather,
وبالتأكيد لا يستحق الأمر أن أتركك تفعل ذلك يا جدي.
and my brother feel bad for me.
ويشعر أخي بالأسى تجاهي.
I went to the Li family on Grandfather's behalf
ذهبت إلى عائلة لي نيابة عن جدي
and returned the manuscript we had taken this morning.
وأعادوا المخطوطة التي أخذناها هذا الصباح.
From this day forward,
ابتداءً من هذا اليوم فصاعداً،
we have absolutely nothing to do with the Li family
ليس لنا أي علاقة على الإطلاق بعائلة لي
or the Tian family.
أو عائلة تيان.
In City Gate Lane, the Li family
في شارع سيتي جيت لين، عائلة لي
means only the four of us!
يعني ذلك نحن الأربعة فقط!
Let's eat well
لنأكل جيداً
and live our lives well!
ولنعيش حياتنا على نحو جيد!
That's easier said than done.
هذا أسهل قولاً من فعلاً.
Mother, I'm starving.
أمي، أنا أتضور جوعاً.
Hurry up and make me some bone broth.
أسرع وأحضر لي بعض مرق العظام.
Go on. Go.
هيا. انطلق.
Fine.
بخير.
I'll go stew it for you right now.
سأقوم بطهيه لك الآن.
Grandfather.
الجد.